Homage to the Buddha Shakyamuni.
Nam Mô Phật Bổn Sư Thích Ca Mâu Ni kính
Greetings to all esteemed fellow practitioners. Today, I, the Mindfulness Meditation Master, would like to
chào các quý đạo hữu hôm nay tâm chú
answer some questions. Regarding the question of
quán xin trả lời một số câu hỏi câu hỏi
practicing the Bodhisattva path, why do we practice to eliminate
tập tu hạnh bồ tát sao lại tu cho hết
suffering? Respectfully, after listening to your
khổ Kính bạch cô chủ nhiệm khi nghe xong
lecture, I thought that
bài giảng của cô em có suy nghĩ là phật
we Buddhists are still practicing to alleviate suffering,
tử chúng em còn đang tu để cho bớt khổ
illness, and loss of possessions—
bớt bệnh tật và thất thoát tài sản những
small sufferings—and yet we still aspire to eliminate them completely.
khổ nhỏ mà còn đang mong cầu cho hết khổ
How can we possibly endure the suffering of a
như vậy làm sao mà chịu được cái khổ của
Bodhisattva? I also thought that if we want to
bồ tát em lại có suy nghĩ nếu mình muốn
practice the Bodhisattva path, we must practice
tu hạnh của bồ tát thì mình phải tu tập
enduring the sufferings of the world to become accustomed to them,
chịu đựng những cái khổ của thế gian để
not just to alleviate suffering. I express my
cho quen dần chứ sao lại tu cho bớt khổ
gratitude for your
em xin tri ân công đức của
merits. Respectfully, esteemed fellow practitioners, our club is the Six Harmonies Practice Club. We have made a vow to cultivate Bodhicitta, protect the Three Jewels, and spread the Dharma throughout the world. This vow of ours is also a practice of the
sự Hạnh Nguyện Của Bồ Tát cái Nguyện Của
Bodhisattva's vows. For example, Bodhisattva Samantabhadra
Bồ Tát ví dụ như là Bồ Tát Phổ Hiền ấy
also has vows. One is to
thì ngài cũng có những cái Nguyện Một là
respectfully pay homage to all Buddhas. Just paying homage to all
kính lễ Chư Phật đấy chỉ kính lễ Chư
Buddhas is enough...  These are the Bodhisattva's vows:
Phật thôi cũng là Nguyện Của Bồ Tát đấy
2. Praising the Tathagata; simply praising the
hai là Xưng Tán Như Lai chỉ có Xưng Tán
Tathagata is also a Bodhisattva's practice.
Giá Như Lai thôi cũng là hạnh của Bồ Tát
3. Extensively cultivating offerings; extensively cultivating offerings is
ba là rộng tu cúng dường thì rộng tu
also a Bodhisattva's practice. 5. Repenting of karmic obstacles;
cúng dường cũng là hạnh của Bồ Tát năm
all
là sám hối nghiệp chưng đ đấy tất cả nh
acts of repentance and karmic retribution, depending on merit, are the
sám hối nghiệp chướng tùy h công đức cầu
Bodhisattva's practice, seeking the Buddha's presence in the world, seeking the Buddha's transformation of the Dharma.
Phật trụ thế cầu Phật Chuyển Pháp đấy
Constantly being in harmony with sentient beings and dedicating merit—all
Hằng thuận chúng sinh hồi hướng tất cả
are Bodhisattva's practices. Respectfully, dear fellow practitioners,
đều là hạnh của Bồ Tát Kính thưa quý đạo
what effect does our practice to liberate ourselves from suffering in our daily lives have on our practice of
gì đối với cái việc chúng ta tập hành
these Bodhisattva practices? Practicing
các cái công hạnh bồ tát này thực hành
Bodhisattva practices is called practicing the
công hạnh bồ đề thì gọi là tập thực hành
Bodhisattva path.
Bồ Tát đạo
Before we
thì trước khi chúng ta trở thành một vị
truly become a Bodhisattva, we must believe in the
Bồ Tát Thực sự thì chúng ta phải tin
Buddha, the Dharma, the Sangha, and the Three Jewels.
phật tin Pháp tin tăng tin Tam Bảo và
We must have the results of our practice before we can encourage others.
thì chúng ta mới đi Khuyến hóa mọi người
Therefore, the first step
được thế cho nên việc tập sự đầu tiên ấy
is to listen to and
là chúng ta phải Nghe giảng Phật pháp
practice the Dharma to resolve our
thực tập Phật pháp để giải quyết khổ cho
own suffering. Only after we have resolved our own suffering can
chính mình thế mình giải quyết khổ được
we tell others to do the same.
cho mình rồi thì mình mới bảo người khác
Buddhist teachings have the value of relieving suffering.
rằng Phật Pháp có giá trị cứu khổ đấy
Practicing the Bodhisattva path must be done step by step, just
thực hành Bồ Tát đạo phải đi từng bước
like the Buddha. When he
một như thế như đức phật ấ Khi ngài
attained enlightenment, under the Bodhi tree, he said, "
thành đạo giữ cội Bồ Đề ngài nói rằng
This Dharma I have realized.
cái pháp này ngài đã chứng đấy Cái pháp
This Dharma I have realized leads to the
này ngài đã chứng cái pháp này đưa đến
cessation of suffering and the
diệt tận các
joy of Nirvana. To eliminate all
khổ được vui Niết Bàn Diệt tất cả khổ
suffering means he must be a truly enlightened being."
đau tức là ngài phải là người thực chững
Similarly, we are bound by our past karma, which
Thế chúng ta cũng vậy cái nhân quả cũ
is evil karma.
của chúng ta là ác nghiệp ác nghiệp cho
Therefore, we are bound by many painful conditions, such as marital
nên chúng ta phải bị những cái ràng buộc
discord, wayward children,
rất là khổ có thể là vợ Chồng bất hòa vợ
loss of property,
con cái hư hỏng thất thoát tài sản bệnh
illness, and suffering. These are the causes
tật ôm đau đấy là những cái nhân mà
we have created over countless lifetimes, and
chúng ta đã tạo từ vô lượng kiếp đến bây
now we must reap the consequences. So
giờ chúng ta phải hái cái quả này Thế
now, let us begin to study Buddhism so that
thì bây giờ chúng ta bắt đầu học phật để
we can apply its teachings. We
chúng ta ứng dụng phật pháp chúng ta
see our karma transforming in
thấy chúng ta chuyển hóa nghiệp ở cái
this place. By carefully analyzing
chỗ này tâm chú quán xin Phân tích kỹ
this, we see our karma transforming.
này thấy mình chuyển hóa
Furthermore, the aspiration to transform karma is
nghiệp và cái nữa là mong cầu chuyển hóa
called the Fourfold Path of the Bodhisattva path,
đường hành Bồ Tát đạo gọi là đồng sự
which means we are the ones who
Nhiếp tức là chúng tôi đang là người
must pay the
phải trả quả
karmic consequences. We practice Buddhism, and
báo chúng tôi thực hành phật pháp và
we receive the benefits.  Happiness, peace, and
chúng tôi được hạnh phúc được an vui
less suffering—that's how
được bớt khổ thế thì chúng ta sau này
we will later become
cái nhân duyên đó sẽ chúng ta sẽ thân
close to those who share the same suffering
cận với những người có đồng cảnh khổ đó
as us, meaning they have also suffered from the
với chúng ta tức là họ cũng đã chịu
negative karma they created, and
nghiệp ác do chính họ họ tạo ra và cái
their negative karma is similar to
nghiệp ác ấy của họ nó giống với nghiệp
our own. Then, when
ác của mình mình đã tu đó Thế thì đến
we encounter them, we will ask, "Is the Buddha's
khi mình đến thì mình mới hỏi là phật
Dharma the wondrous path to liberation from suffering?
pháp là Vi Diệu là con đường cứu khổ
Before, I did this, I suffered
trước kia tôi cũng làm thế này tôi cũng
this, I practiced this way.
bị cái quả khổ này tôi tu thế này Cho
Therefore, I have transformed. So,
nên tôi có chuyển hóa cho nên cái việc
our practice is to first save ourselves, and
tu của mình là trước lo độ mình sau gì
then save sentient beings. Those of you who
sau lo độ chúng sinh các quý Đạo ếu ạ
practice the Bodhisattva path must first save yourselves,
hành Bồ Tát đạo thì B giờ cũng phải là
then save sentient beings.
trước lo độ mình sau lo độ chúng sinh
You must be someone who has experienced it first before you can
mình phải là người trải nghiệm đã thì
speak about it. If you speak about something
mình mới nói ra được Còn nếu như cái mà
you haven't practiced or proven,
mình chưa thực hành chưa thực Chứng mình
it becomes mere speculation; it doesn't
nói ra thì nó rơi vào hí luận nó không
benefit you or others. The Buddha taught that you
lợi ích cho người thì Đức Phật dạy không
shouldn't speak about such things. Therefore, those who
nên nói điều đó cho nên những người mà
aspire to practice the Bodhisattva path are
mong muốn hành Bồ Tát đạo thì là những
those who truly practice the Dharma.
con người chân thật thực hành pháp cho
So, all of us
nên tất cả chúng ta
in this...  What we need to cultivate is that
trong các cái điều cần tu của chúng ta
we study Buddhist teachings, we
Đấy là chúng ta học phật pháp chúng ta
see the preciousness of Buddhism, we pay homage to the
thấy Phật pháp cao quý chúng ta kính lễ
Buddhas, we repent of our karmic obstacles,
Chư Phật chúng ta sám hối nghiệp chướng
we rejoice in merit, we
chúng ta tùy hỉ công đức đấy chúng ta
widely practice offerings according to
rộng tu cúng dường đấy theo cái duyên
our circumstances. Why is this offering
của mình cái cúng dường này thì sao lại
called "widely practicing offerings"? It means that above, we
gọi là rộng tu cúng dường Tức là trên
offer to the Buddha, the Dharma, and the Sangha;
thì cúng dường đến phật đến pháp đến
below, we offer to our parents
tăng dưới thì cúng dường cho cho cha mẹ
and all beings. We still make
gì và muôn loài chúng ta vẫn cả cúng
offerings to create merit to dedicate to all
dường tạo Phước để hồi hướng cho cả
beings with whom we have a karmic connection, those
những chúng sinh có duyên với mình mà
with whom we committed evil in previous lives—that is, our
kiếp trước mình đã làm ác với họ tức là
karmic enemies. In that, we are both offering and
oan gia dĩ chủ ấy thì ở đấy nó vừa cúng
repenting. Therefore,
dường Vừa gì vừa sám hối thế cho nên
on this path of practicing the Bodhisattva path,
trên con đường hành Bồ Tát đạo này con
people must endure many
người phải chịu rất là nhiều những cái
hardships to cultivate. For example,
gian khổ để tu hành ví dụ thế này chúng
we might face karmic consequences such as an unhappy marriage,
ta bị một cái quả báo là vợ chồng không
perhaps a husband who gambles, perhaps a loss of
có thể là chồng cờ bạc có thể thất thoát
property, perhaps a wayward child. But
tài sản có thể con hư thế nhưng mà bây
now, if the husband and child don't believe in or practice
giờ chồng và con không tin tu theo Phật
Buddhism, and we alone believe and practice,
Pháp một mình mình tin mình tu theo Phật
then we must endure and cultivate—that is,
pháp thì chúng ta phải Nhẫn nhục mà tu
endure suffering to cultivate. This
đấy là chịu gì Chịu khổ để tu hành đấy
may be part of the process.  When I practice Buddhism,
có thể trong cái Quá trình mình tu hành
my family members may not understand and cause
thì người nhà mình chưa hiểu sẽ gây
me distress. Therefore, I must be patient and
phiền não cho mình thế Mình phải Nhẫn
tolerant in my practice. This is called patience and
nhục mình tu hành đấy vẫn gọi là Nhẫn
tolerance, to practice the Dharma, to experience the
nhục để thực hành pháp để chứng nghiệm
Dharma, and to transmit the Buddha's teachings. That's
pháp để chuyển tải Phật pháp ấy thế cho
why those who practice the Bodhisattva path must always be
nên là người hành Bồ Tát đạo là lúc nào
patient and tolerant. People in the world may be
cũng phải nhẫn dục thế còn người ở đời
patient and tolerant, but they don't
thì họ Nhẫn nhục nhưng mà họ lại không
have the ideal of practicing the Bodhisattva path. But
có cái lý tưởng là hành Bồ Tát đạo nhưng
we still have to be patient and tolerant. For example, if we practice
vẫn phải Nhẫn nhục chứ ví dụ chúng ta
patiently and tolerantly,
Nhẫn nhục chúng ta tu thì chúng ta
we transform our
chuyển nghiệp thì chúng ta có chuyển
karma, and then we can bring
nghiệp rồi chúng ta lại có thể làm lợi
benefit and happiness to our husbands and children.
ích hạnh phúc cho chồng mình con mình
We then transmit the truth of the Buddha's teachings
rồi mình đi chuyển tải Phật pháp sự thật
to many people. And
này đến cho nhiều người thế và mình
what we transform is the connection we have with
chuyển hóa gì mình có duyên với chính
our husbands and children. The practice
chồng mình và con mình chính việc tu tập
within our own homes is also practicing the
trong nhà mình cũng là mình đang hành Bồ
Bodhisattva path, Venerable Masters. Why? Because my
Tát đạo đấy các quý Đạ Hữu Á vì sao vì
husband has wrong views, my children have wrong views, are immoral and
chồng thì tà kiến con thì tà kiến vô đạo
corrupt, but we have a connection with them
rồi hư hỏng thế nhưng mình với họ có
now. We strive to
duyên hiện tại bây giờ mình nỗ lực thực
practice the Buddha's teachings so that we can dedicate the merit to them and
hành Phật pháp để gì để mình hồi hướng
to ourselves, to transform our
cho họ hồi hướng cho mình để chuyển hóa
shared karma, and from there,
cái cộng nghiệp và từ đó thì cái mối
our relationship with them will become better.  The
quan hệ của mình với họ sẽ trở thành
cause and effect of karma leads to goodness.
thành trong nhân quả thành cái lành
Then, do we make a vow? If
Thiện thế rồi mình có phát nguyện không
we make a vow, if we make a vow
Mình có phát nguyện mình có phát nguyện
that wherever we are born and meet them again, we will
là mình sinh ra đâu gặp lại họ thì mình
bring the Buddha's
cũng mang Phật pháp truyển Tải đến cho
teachings to them, that means we are practicing the Bodhisattva path
họ thế tức là mình đang hành Bồ Tát đạo
right in our own homes. Therefore, a
ngay chính trong nhà mình nữa đó Thế cho
person who practices Buddhism and develops
nên là người tu tập Phật Pháp mà phát bồ
Bodhicitta is someone who, in the present moment,
đề tâm ấ thì là người vừa trong hiện tại
benefits, experiences the Dharma, and
làm lợi ích chứng nghiệm Pháp rồi trải
experiences the happiness of the Dharma. Then, that person
nghiệm hạnh phúc của Pháp rồi người đó
forms a Bodhisattva connection with all their relatives
lại kết duyên bồ đề với tất cả thân bằng
and sentient beings. Therefore, a
Quyến thuộc và chúng sinh thế cho nên là
person who wants to practice the Bodhisattva path
người tu tập mà muốn hành Bồ Tát đạo thì
must practice the
phải thực hành các pháp để chứng nghiệm
Dharma to experience its benefits, to experience
pháp để thấy được lợi ích của Pháp phải
peace, to experience
trải nghiệm được sự an lành phải trải
liberation. Dear fellow
nghiệm được sự giải thoát Kính thưa các
practitioners, in this Dharma assembly, you
quý đạo hữu đấy ở trong đạo tràng thì
see that if those who
các quý Đạo Hữu thấy nếu như những ai mà
practice Buddhism diligently
tu tập Phật Pháp mà họ tinh tấn họ
transform their karma and have the
chuyển hóa nghiệp rồi họ lại có cái Tâm
Bodhicitta mind, wishing for the Buddha's teachings to
Bồ Đề mong muốn cho Phật pháp được lan
spread widely to everyone, they will certainly be
truyền được rộng đến cho mọi người thì
diligent. But what about those who only come to
tấn thế nhưng mà với những người chỉ đến
practice Buddhism and only wish to transform
tu Phật Pháp mà chỉ mong muốn chuyển hóa
their own homes?  So, they transform their karma a
cho nhà mình thôi thì chuyển hóa một
little, and then they have good fortune, and then
chút rồi Xong rồi thì họ lại có phước
they go back to doing business.
rồi thì họ lại l vào làm ăn kinh tế họ
They don't practice anymore, they
không tu nữa họ không tu nữa mà họ cũng
don't bother bringing the Dharma to
chẳng buồn mang Phật pháp đến cho mọi
others anymore. That's not called practicing the
người nữa thì đấy không phải gọi là hành
Bodhisattva path. That's just entering the Dharma to practice,
Bồ Tát đạo đấy là chỉ vào đạo để tu tập
to pray for a little merit for themselves, to
để cầu cho mình được có một chút phúc
enjoy the merit, to enjoy the merit. When the merit runs out, they
rồi hưởng phúc hưởng phúc Hết Phúc khổ
return to the Dharma and practice again, that's
rồi lại vào Phật pháp lại tu thế thôi
all. But those who have a kind heart and compassion, who have developed a little, they enter the Dharma, diligently practice, transform their karma, and then diligently share the happiness they have experienced with others, guiding and transmitting it to many people.
cho người khác đều nhiều người được thực
They see
hành được hạnh phúc và họ thấy con đường
this path of the Dharma as so precious that they
phật pháp này quý báo quá cho nên họ
strive tirelessly,
tinh tấn không ngơi nghỉ và họ miệt mài
guiding and encouraging others. That's what we
hướng dẫn cho người khác sách tấn người
call
khác thì người đó gọi là tập sự thực
practicing the Bodhisattva path. Therefore,
hành Bồ Tát đạo đó Thế cho nên Phật tử
we lay Buddhists still have to do things for ourselves and others, we must
tại gia chúng ta vẫn phải có gì vẫn phải
practice the Dharma ourselves, and when we
tự lợi lợi tha tự mình thực hành Phật
benefit, we must spread the
pháp được lợi tự mình phải truyển Tải
Dharma to everyone. That's what we call practicing the Bodhisattva path.  This is the
phật pháp đến cho mọi người thế gọi là
practice of the Bodhisattva path. But let's
thực hành Bồ Tát đạo nha Nhưng mà chúng
not forget that only doing things for one's own benefit is
ta đừng quên là chỉ làm mỗi lợi ích cho
not called practicing the
mình thôi thì không gọi là thực hành Bồ
Bodhisattva path. Therefore, all Buddhists in the
Tát đạo cho nên tất cả phật tử trong câu
Kṣitigarbha Bodhisattva group, if anyone
Lộc bộ Cúc bài chúng ta nếu ai tinh tấn
diligently practices Bodhisattva virtues,
Bồ Đề tinh tấn thực hành công hạnh bồ đề
we call them those who are beginning to
thì chúng ta gọi là những người bước đầu
practice the Bodhisattva path. Even lay people can
thực hành Bồ Tát đạo đó người tại gia
do the same to benefit themselves.
của chúng ta cũng làm được lợi ích như
This merit and karmic reward will
vậy đấy thì cái công đức Phước báo này
allow us to diligently practice for many lifetimes, and
khiến cho chúng ta nhiều đời nhiều kiếp
eventually achieve Supreme Enlightenment.
được tinh tấn sau sẽ thành tựu Vô Thượng
If we do not
Bồ Đề Nếu kiếp này chúng ta không tinh
diligently practice the Bodhisattva path in this lifetime, then in some
tấn tập thực hành Bồ Tát đạo thì đến một
lifetime we will still have to take those
kiếp nào đó chúng ta vẫn phải đi những
first steps because to escape suffering, we must
bước đi đầu tiên vì muốn thoát khổ thì
practice the Dharma of liberation. To escape
phải thực hành pháp thoát khổ muốn thoát
suffering, we must create our own liberation
khổ thì phải tự mình làm cho mình thoát
and practice the Dharma of giving. Only then will
khổ và thực hành pháp bố thí thì chúng
we have the merit to help ourselves escape
ta mới có công đức giúp cho mình thoát
suffering. Therefore,
khổ được cho nên tự mình tu tập Phật
cultivating and transmitting the Dharma is the
pháp chuyển tải Phật Pháp là con đường
noble path, the first step in practicing the
cao quý là bước đầu tập sự hành Bồ Tát
Bodhisattva path, benefiting ourselves and others, leading to liberation, Nirvana, and
đạo tự lợi lợi tha hướng tới giải thoát
Supreme Enlightenment.
niết bàn hướng tới Vô Thượng Bồ Đề chúng
Let us all diligently practice together. Wishing you all the
ta hãy cùng nhau tinh tấn chúc các quý
best.  With diligent effort, Namo Buddha Shakyamuni
đạo hữu tinh tấn Nam Mô Phật Bổn Sư
[music]
[âm nhạc]
Ni n
Ni n